George T. Quick Papers
George T. Quick Papers
1835-1911
Quick, George T.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Union soldier (circa 1834-1911) and British immigrant who served as a recruitment officer for the Independent Battalion, New York Volunteers, and was subsequently stationed at Point Lookout, MD, Yorktown and Eastville, VA, and Morris Island, SC. Collection includes correspondence (1862-1911); personal and company military documents, including commissions, discharge papers, lists of contraband, muster rolls, general and special orders, accounts of courts-martial, recruitment records, receipts, requisitions, and rosters; legal and financial records, including pension statements, tax receipts, and wills.
149534
Biographical History
George T. Quick (circa 1833-1911) was a British emigré to the United States. A carpenter by trade, he served in the Union Army (1861-1864) as a recruitment officer for the Independent Battalion, New York Volunteers, and was subsequently stationed at Point Lookout, MD; Yorktown and Eastville, VA; and Morris Island, SC.
Quick was born in London, England, in 1833 or 1834. It is not known when he emigrated to the United States, but he was living in New York City at the outbreak of the Civil War. He enlisted for three months' service in May 1861 and was mustered out as a sergeant in August 1861. He subsequently re-enlisted in February 1862 and in June and July 1862 recruited men in New York City for the Independent Battalion of the New York Volunteers. In October 1862 he was commissioned a second lieutenant and was named regimental and post adjutant while his unit was stationed at Point Lookout, Maryland, and Yorktown and Eastville, Virginia. His unit was transferred subsequently to Morris Island, South Carolina, and also spent time in Beaufort, South Carolina, serving as part of the Union forces besieging Charleston. During this time Quick was in charge of a company in the regiment. He was commissioned a first lieutenant in October 1863. In February 1864 he was discharged from the service, though it appears he may have continued to recruit for the army.
Quick was a carpenter by trade and sometimes held positions of responsibility in the Carpenters and Joiners Union. He was also a minor official in the Grand Army of the Republic (GAR), a veterans' organization. The evidence of the papers suggests that Quick was married twice. His first wife was named Margaret; it is not clear when she died. His second wife, Eliza Ann, died in 1890. These papers suggest that after his second marriage Quick moved from New York City to the vicinity of Nyack and Piermont, New York. He died around 1911.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George T. Quick Papers, 1835-1911, contain correspondence, military records, legal and financial records, and memorabilia.
Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing letters from 1862 to 1911. Although the larger part is official military correspondence, there are some personal letters from his wife Margaret and his brother William that report on conditions at home. A letter from 1866 concerns payment for a trade union representative at the New York funeral of Abraham Lincoln, and other letters relate to Quick's activities with the Grand Army of the Republic (GAR).
Military correspondence deals with a variety of official business matters. Many of the letters are copies of originals. Among the matters treated are contraband (Negro slaves that had escaped to the Union lines), the security of the camp and hospital at Point Lookout, Maryland, the refusal of a commission to a deserter, the management of the savings of the company commanded by Quick, the delivery of supplies, and disciplinary matters. Noteworthy is a letter from a Sergeant Claiborne to Quick's commanding officer complaining about the default by Quick on a personal debt. Letters from a lieutenant in Quick's battalion deal with recruiting duties, the possibility of the writer's promotion, and the court-martial of the battalion commander.
Military records, 1861-1911, are divided into personal and company categories. Included in the personal section are Quick's discharge papers of 1861, his commissions as second and first lieutenant, muster rolls documenting the fact that he was mustered into those ranks, a statement of his appointment as sergeant, a certificate giving him authority to recruit for the Army, and certificates documenting his membership in the Grand Army of the Republic.
The company section contains administrative materials. An account book lists amounts of equipment and mess supplies issued to company personnel. The contraband lists give names and dates of transmittal of escaped Negro slaves. The morning reports, muster rolls, and personnel reports contain information about the soldiers in Quick's command. The general orders, some of which are printed material, represent decisions of the army high command. The special orders are from lower-ranking commanders and deal with particular local situations. The provision returns, receipts, and requisitions detail various transactions involved in equipping the company.
Of particular note are the charges and specifications and the records of proceedings of courts-martial. All are handwritten documents. There are charges related to desertion, disobedience of orders, and other offenses. Also here are the proceedings of a court-martial related to absence without leave and another related to desertion.
Legal and financial records, 1835-1903, include documents such as wills and accounts payable books. The accounts payable record details expenditures made on behalf of Lawrence Quick, who may have been a son or brother. An 1867 deed documents the sale of property by Richard G. Perry to Quick's wife, Eliza Ann. Among the wills and related documents are the will of Eliza Ann Quick, a letter testamentary related to that will, and the will of Jacob Perry. It is not clear what relationship the latter has to the rest of the collection, although it may involve the above-mentioned property sold to Quick's second wife. The certificate of non-liability for military service seems to have been issued to a relative of Eliza Ann Quick.
Memorabilia, 1857-1886, contains mostly printed material. The constitution of the Sons of Veterans is a printed document of this auxiliary of the GAR. The book of English ballads is incomplete. The phrenological analysis of George T. Quick was apparently made by a professional phrenologist.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Military files are subdivided into personal and company files and within that arranged alphabetically. Legal and financial records and Memorabilia are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
also has numerous collections relating to the America Civil War and to military history; please refer to for a complete listing. See the
Sons of Veterans, New York Division, Collection
for more information about this auxiliary of the GAR.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Civil War (U.S.); Quick, George T.; United States. -- Army -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources.; United States. -- Army -- Officers.; United States. -- Army. -- New York Volunteers.; Soldiers -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources.; United States -- History, Military -- To 1900 -- Sources.; Correspondence.; Military records.; Muster rolls.; Wills.; Soldiers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1967.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1862-1866; 1874,; 1911; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Envelopes (Box 1)
- Military
  - Personal
    - Certificate of authority to recruit, 1864 (Box 1)
    - Certificates of the Grand Army of the Republic, 1880; 1881 (Box 1)
    - Commissions, 1862; 1863 (Box 1)
    - Discharges, 1861 (Box 1)
    - Muster rolls, 1863; 1864 (Box 1)
    - Record of service, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Company
    - Account book of clothing, camp and garrison equipage, 1863 (Box 1)
    - Blank forms, undated (Box 1)
    - Court martials, 1862; charges and specifications, records of proceedings (Box 1)
    - Lists of contraband, 1862 (Box 1)
    - Morning reports, 1862; 1863 (Box 1)
    - Muster rolls, 1862; 1863 (Box 1)
    - Orders
      - General, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
      - Special, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
    - Personnel reports, 1862; 1863 (Box 1)
    - Personnel roster, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
    - Provision returns, ordinance reports and invoices, clothing, camp and garrison equipage prices, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
    - Receipts: ordnance, commissary, contraband, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
    - Requisitions, 1863 (Box 1)
    - Volunteer enlistment statement, certificate entitling discharged soldier to pay, Discharge statement, Officer's certificate of soldier's disability, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
- Legal and financial records
  - Accounts payable record, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Deed, 1867 (Box 1)
  - Pension statements, 1898-1907 (Box 1)
  - Tax receipts, 1890-1895 (Box 1)
  - Wills and codicils, 1835; 1890 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous receipts and a certificate of non-liability for military service, 1850-1903 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Constitution of Sons of Veterans and a political cartoon, 1886; printed material (Box 1)
  - Fragment of book on English ballads, undated (Box 1)
  - Phrenological analysis of George T. Quick, 1857 (Box 1)
Selected index to correspondence
Letters to George T. Quick are marked "to GTQ."
Barstow, Capt. Wilson Sep 15 1862, Fort Monroe, VA, to Capt. H.C. Van Kirk Oct 17 1862, Fort Monroe, VA, to Capt. H. J. Van Kirk Nov 22 1862, Fort Monroe, VA, to Capt. N. Hager
Brown, Maj. John Carter Nov 11 1862, Yorktown, VA, to Brig. Genl. G. K. Warren Dec 2 1862, Dec 16 1862, Feb 24 1863, Eastville, VA, to Capt. William M. Boone
Claiborne, Sgt. J. Alfred Oct 21 1863, Morris Island, SC, to Capt. Edward Eddy, Jr.
Coffin, Capt. E. W. Jan 30 1863, Yorktown, VA, to GTQ
Confort?, Lt. Col. Jun 23 1862, Yorktown, VA, to G. S. Halemand?
Douds, J. Clyde Oct 29 1862, Near Suffolk, VA, to H. J. Van Kirk
Dunbar, Lt. C.L. May 29 1862, Yorktown, VA, to GTQ Jun 30 1862, Yorktown, VA, to GTQ Jul 9 1862, Yorktown, VA, to GTQ
Engelbert, Albert J. et al Sep 20 1866, New York, to Carpenters and Joiners Union
Ferris, Capt. Thad, C. Feb 22 1863, Eastville, VA, to Maj. J. Carter Brown
Langbein, Julius May 27 1874, New York, to GTQ
Parkinson, E.C. Jul 13 1874, Boonville, NY to GTQ Oct 17 1874, New York, to GTQ
Pease, Lt. Harry E. Jun 25 1863, St. Helena Island, NC, to [ ] Hughes
Quick, Lt. George T. Nov 10 1862, Yorktown, VA, to T. C. Ferris May 18 1863, Beaufort, SC, to Col. Charles Halpin (2 copies) Oct 18 1863, Morris Island, to Maj. Schmitt (copy) Oct 28 1863, Morris Island, to Maj. Schmitt (copy) Nov 1863, Morris Island, to Capt. Adrian Terry Nov 19 1863, Morris Island, to Brig. Gen. L. Thomas Nov 29 1863, Morris Island, to Maj. M. Schmitt Jan 8 1864, Morris Island, to Capt. W.L. M. Burger Mar 9 1874, Nyack, to Capt. W.L. M. Burger (copy)
Quick, Margaret Dec 3 1863, New York, to GTQ Dec 18 1863, New York, to GTQ Jan 4 1864, New York, to GTQ
Quick, William J. Nov 30 1863, Brooklyn, to GTQ
Ramsay, W.R. Nov 9 1863, Beaufort, SC, to GTQ (copy)
Rockwell, William Feb 20 1863, Point Lookout, MD, to Maj. John Carter Brown
Sawyer?, Charles W. et al Nov 18 1863, Morris Island, SC, to GTQ
Schmitt, Maj. M. May 16 1863, Beaufort, SC, to Col. C.G. Halpin
Smith, Joseph R. Nov 22 1862, Washington City, to W. H. Gardner (copy)
Topping, Edward D. Mar 3 1864, East Moriches, to GTQ
Tyler, Capt. C.R. Mar 23 1863, ?Drummondtown, to GTQ
Wagner, Clinton Sep 18 1862, Point Lookout, MD, to [N. Hager?] Sep 23 1862, Point Lookout, MD, to N. Hager Sep 28 1862, [Pt. Lookout, MD, to [H. J.] Van Kirk
[unsigned] Oct 19 1862, Point Lookout, MD, to H. J. Van Kirk
[unsigned] Jun 1863, Beaufort, SC, to Capt. R. Holmes
-----, Tom Mar 24 1864, Camp. 124th Regt., to GTQ Feb 11 1911, Albany, to Georg H. Quick